For over a century, the legendary tales
that have surrounded our great British
airfields have inspired generations of
people, including me. Which is why I am
on a personal mission to cross the UK to
visit some of our most important
airfields to understand not just about
their contribution to our past, but
importantly, how many of them have
helped define our future. From the UK's
first flight through to groundbreaking
innovations such as carbon fiber and the
jet engine and the extraordinary efforts
spent on preserving our aviation
heritage. Join me as I explore the story
of the airfields that have helped shape
Britain and the world.
I'm here in Farra, the birthplace of
British aviation. And it's said that no
other single location in the world has
contributed quite as much to the
evolution of aeronautical science as
this place over such a long period of
time with aviation development in
Britain and was the site of the Royal
Aircraft Establishment, [music] the
military science research facility.
During the 20th century, the testing of
observation balloons and airships by the
army quickly developed into
groundbreaking experiments. It remains
world famous for its air show and
specialist aviation knowledge. Today,
the Farra Air Science Trust, known as
FAST, are the guardians of Farra's
engineering legacy.
How important was the RAE and Farborra
in the history of global aviation?
>> Oh, enormously, enormously important. I
mean, it brought science and technology
into aviation which was quite a young uh
sport in those early days. But
effectively, you had a large number of
departments that did aerodynamic
structures, engines, materials. We tend
to associate the evolution of the
aircraft with the first world war. But
even before the outbreak of the war, RE
here was up and running in a very
far-sighted way.
>> Farra was always looking 15 years ahead
to to actually develop new systems right
through to the Cold War. If a new
aircraft had to be built, the air staff
came to us and would say what technology
do we have in 15 years time because
it'll take that long to build the
airplane.
>> So for over a century, RE has been a
global center of excellence. Oh,
absolutely.
>> But what happens to the RA?
>> It started to close down in 1990s when
government no longer wished to fund
centrally fund aviation research. But
there was 100 years of research here. It
was all secret. Nobody knew very little
that went on. So we started collecting
all the artifacts and the records from
the libraries. The RE had a superb
historical library which went back to
1898. We collected all that. So now
we're keeping the legacy in the museum
and making it available for the public.
>> Well, I've just touched the surface. So
let's continue our tour.
>> The museum's collection is enormous,
holding over half a million items. It
includes machinery, photographs, films,
and books, all relating to its
illustrious history.
>> Wow.
>> Just remind me how many of these
containers you've got again. We've got
18 40 foot containers and two 20 foot
containers full of artifacts.
>> A Concord engine there.
>> That's a Concord.
>> That's That's a Concord. That's a 593.
>> What's that do there?
>> That's with There's two helicopters
through there. There's There's a Lynx
and a Scout. A Navy Scout.
>> You're joking. That's That's the design
of the atom bomb itself. But it's not
just the paperwork and mechanical parts
that have been kept. Their collection of
flying clothing [music] has more than
250 items of protective gear.
This helmet is clearly in advance of the
Second World War version.
>> Yes, really. This is late 60s, early '7s
where Americans had loaned us some suits
when we were looking at man's space
program for Great Britain. And these
were some of the very early space suits
when we had a program to put man into
space.
One thing that strikes me, Graeme, being
surrounded by all of these artifacts is
the millions of pounds and dollars that
went into developing each and every one
of them. And yet now you could say,
well, they're sort of worthless, but at
the same time priceless in the story of
aviation.
>> Yeah, absolutely. You have to understand
the past to appreciate what's going to
happen in the future.
Farra's role was obviously vital in the
development of aeronautical engineering
in this country, but it took an American
cowboy to get the British aviation
industry as a whole off the ground quite
literally.
[music]
In 1896, the Wild West came to Britain
in the form of Samuel Cody.
But it wasn't just cowboys and Indians
that captivated this American showman.
His interesting kites started as a
hobby. He found that flying kites drew a
crowd. Therefore, he persisted in flying
bigger kites. He developed a system
whereby pilot kites would carry a wire
into the sky and that wire would act as
an aerial railway for the anchoring of a
man carrying element which go up and
down the wire at will.
Cody believed his manlifting kites could
be used for military observation
purposes as an alternative to balloons.
These, unlike kites, couldn't be
deployed in strong [music] winds. But he
also perceived they could have an engine
in. And the first motorized kite that
[music] he built wasn't big enough to
carry a passenger, but it flew tethered.
Uh but it demonstrated that that with
power, [music] you could get airborne
from the ground without having to use a
string of wind. In 1906, the army was
convinced and Cody was made head of the
design and manufacturer of kites at the
balloon factory at Farra. But he had
grander plans and he began work on his
[music] first airplane. Cody understood
it had to be fairly lightweight, but if
you're flying on cloth as a kite with a
single layer of cloth supporting you,
the wing loading, the the pounds per
square inch that you can develop is
quite low. So to get enough lift to
build a big mass, you need a big
airplane. And Cody understood that and
his airplanes were always big.
>> On the 16th of October 1908, Cody made
history at Farra. His British Army
airplane number one left the ground and
flew 1,390
ft at a speed of 25 to 30 mph. The
flight only lasted 27 [music] seconds,
but it was the first powered flight in
Britain. Over
the next two years, Cody continued to
improve his designs, and in 1910, he
made the longest flight [music] in
England, a record 4 hours and 47
minutes. But unfortunately, it wasn't to
last. And on the 7th of August, 1913,
tragedy struck at Farra.
Cody was flying over what's now the
airfield with a passenger when something
on the aircraft broke. Whatever that
was, it caused such a violent maneuver
by the aircraft that the passenger and
the pilot both fell out of the airplane.
The 7th of August 1913 was the day Cody
died, not in an airplane, but having
fallen out of one. No seat belt, no
parachute.
>> Cody was a showman, a cowboy by trade,
and a real man of the people. He
received a full military funeral.
But with the outbreak of World War I,
just a year after his death, he was
virtually all but forgotten.
By 1916, the workforce here at Farmer
had expanded to nearly 4,000, and they
were working around the clock,
desperately trying to make up for lost
time.
>> Ian, nice to see you.
>> And you, good morning. Where better
place to talk about the development of
early aircraft than here in your
workshop. Pleasure to have you here.
Now, you've got a lovely example here of
what was going on at the time to try and
create workable airframes and workable
surfaces on aircraft. I mean, for those
early pilots being up in the sky
surrounded by nothing more than timber
and linen must have been terrifying.
>> Well, yes. It looks very flimsy. It's a
bit of cloth, bit of wood, but once it's
put together, once it's been treated,
um, then it becomes quite a stable and
strong environment.
>> But this is the technology of the
Victorian era.
>> It certainly is, which is why so many
cabinet makers went into aircraft
production in World War I.
>> But it just highlights how difficult and
how dangerous these early days of
aircraft development were.
>> Exactly. but also in the manufacturer
that um one of the things that's done to
the fabric is what we call doping.
Doping being uh laying this painting on
this substance which stretches the
fabric and makes it weatherproof
>> and it gives it that kind of drumlike.
>> Exactly. But it also when you're doing
it gives off a lot of vapor and at the
beginning that wasn't recognized and so
quite a few ladies and men died as a
consequence of inhaling that vapor. The
rate of aviation development [music]
from 1908 to 1914 was staggering. By the
start of World War I, there were just 40
aircraft in the UK, but by the end of
the war, there were more than 20,000.
The initial requirement was for aircraft
that would be able to fly over enemy
lines and observe what was going on. But
then of course when you have aircraft
that are flying over to observe the
enemy decide they've got aircraft that
will shoot you down. So you have to
evolve another type of aircraft which is
an offensive aircraft that can defend
your observation aircraft
>> and that's the birth of the fighter.
>> Exactly. Exactly. And that in a way
gives Farra its purpose for the rest of
its life.
>> It certainly does. The aircraft industry
was established and Farra was then
dedicated to pure research um and
development and test. During World War
I, Farra had [music] built over 500
aircraft and repaired thousands more.
And by 1919, with the conflict over, the
emphasis for the Royal Aircraft
Establishment was now on science and
research. The inter war years saw
development continue [music] at an
incredible rate. While Britain was
suffering in the Great Depression, the
RAE were undertaking important
developmental work [music] on drones,
missiles. They even managed to
successfully launch an aircraft from a
Royal Navy destroyer by catapult. The
engineers and scientists were putting
Farra on the global map.
Farra's development at the beginning of
the 20th century had been slow and
steady, but World War I had forced them
into a rapid expansion. British aviation
had to improve and develop to become as
good, [music] if not better, than the
competition. And with World War II just
around the corner, the Royal Aircraft
establishment had to be at its best.
Well, by the beginning of the war in
1939, Farra once again was coming into
its own. But if I'd have had the chance
to wander around the airfield and throw
open any of the hanger doors, who knows
what I would have seen under
investigation. But this once
confidential report might give me a few
clues. It's an historical summary of the
Royal Aircraft establishment between
1918 and 1948. But if we just flick
through to the beginning of the war to
1939 to 1940, well, the headings here
really do tell you all that you need to
know. The aerodynamic department were
looking at low-speed wind tunnel
testing. The instrument and photographic
department were investigating the
development of the gyro gun site. The
mechanical test department, well, they
were looking at the business of
self-sealing fuel tanks. But this is
absolutely fascinating. In 1940, the
experimental flying department received
the first meases ME 109 fighter to be
captured and brought it here for
rigorous trials. and it was flown by one
flying officer J Peabody. But I'm sure
he could never have imagined himself
that so soon after the start of the war
he'd find himself flying an enemy
fighter, learning crucial lessons that
he could feed back to the squadrons on
the front line. It's fascinating to see
the amount of detailed research that was
being carried out, much of which at the
time would have been secret. Even with
the war raging around them, they were
trying to improve pressure injection in
engines and [clears throat] the effects
of GeForce on pilots. When you look at
the breadth of endeavor and inquiry that
was going on here, no surprise that some
of the nation's best scientists and
engineers were recruited to come here to
Farra to carry on this vital war work.
One of those bright minds was engineer
John Charley. He was recruited by the
RAE straight from university in 1943.
>> I was appointed to the flight test
division of aerodynamics department.
Although I knew nothing about it, that
was where I was being put posted. And
this chapter had been sent to collect me
took me into the hanger and behind the
screens was our first jetpropelled
airplane. I became something of um an
expert on [music] the jet propelled a
airplane in its early experimental form.
One of the pioneers tasked with testing
aircraft was Captain Eric Winkl Brown of
the Royal Navy. He flew a staggering 487
different types of aircraft. It's a
record that is [music] unlikely ever to
be broken.
Farber, frankly, in the war years was
like a pressure pot because
naturally the enemies was improving the
performance of their aircraft all the
time and we always had to try and keep a
jump ahead of them if possible. But the
Germans were very advanced in their
performance aircraft and uh so it was
quite [music] quite a difficult
struggle. With World War II raging,
there was no time to waste. In 1944,
test flights from Farra totaled over
8,000 hours, an average of 23 hours a
day.
>> The test was [music] to take a Spitfire,
climb to 40,000 ft, put the nose down,
and tell him that the speed would
increase and on the way down he'd find
he'd lose control. But don't worry about
it. By the time you get down to 15,000
ft, it'll be back again. and all will be
well. And he believed me.
>> In some airplanes, they lost control. In
others, the stick got so hard that you
couldn't move the stick. So, there's
nothing you could [music] do about it.
You sat there and couldn't pull out
until you got down to the lower heights.
The characteristics [music]
would get back to normal.
>> But it wasn't just British planes that
were being tested. Farra's hangers were
also filled with countless German
aircraft, including the famous
Messesmith ME109.
>> We had quite a few
aircraft during the war years land in
Britain. Uh because they were damaged,
shut down, whatnot, and uh provided they
were repable, we did so and then flew
them to see how good they were.
I found German aircraft were very
logical in some of their aspects in the
cockpit. For example, they used
electrics a lot more than we did. And
also they had colorcoded all things in
the cockpit. For example, all the
instruments that were associated with
oil were a brown color. Anything
associated with oxygen was blue. And so
they went on color coding all. So I
subtly enjoyed and had a very high
regard for German aircraft at that time.
>> Being a test pilot was a hazardous
occupation and sadly during World War II
nine pilots lost their lives at [music]
Farra. Flying at up to 700 m an hour
wasn't a job for the faint-hearted.
Well, the thing we were trying to do um
was to make sure that our pilots, our
our aircraft were better controlled for
operational purposes fighting than the
enemy. And in that case, you wanted them
to make sure they go as fast as they
could and also that they could be
controlled in in combat.
>> The rate of testing was extremely high.
I have in my log book I think some five
occasions where I flew eight different
types of aircraft in one day. That is
really pushing it because of this
situation. This may have accounted for a
number of the fatalities we had because
unless you really prepare yourself for
this, you are going to get into trouble.
I'm only 5 feet seven. I've saved myself
two or three times by seeing the crash
coming and curling up in the cockpit.
Maybe I was overzealous in preparation,
but it paid off. I'd be here still.
Thanks to the pioneering work of the
likes of Captain Brown and Sir Charley,
flying has become much safer. Their work
has informed subsequent generations of
aerospace engineers, helping them to
design and build much safer planes. And
of course, with the advent of modern
technology, many of those riskier tests
can now be undertaken from the safety of
modern simulators, which means that I
get to have a go from the safety of the
ground.
Alan
>> Jules,
>> very nice to meet you.
>> Good to meet you.
>> Now, flying is in your blood. You've got
many thousands of hours flying behind
you.
>> A few. Yes. Yes.
>> And you've taught many others to fly, of
course. Indeed.
>> Yes.
>> When we see on the news the launch of a
new airliner. I'm thinking in particular
of the latest huge aircraft that's now
out there from Boeing.
>> Just how risky is it for the test pilots
taking something like that up? It's not
as risky as it was. The lessons that
were learned, the science of aeronautics
has improved uh and our knowledge has
has improved. So before an aircraft even
flies nowadays, the the the computer
modeling that that that is used with
again it's handinhand with computer
technology shows that the machine is
going to fly and it probably will
achieve the targets that was set out
from the drawing board. That said, they
still don't fully know. Hence, they've
got to get airborne and try it out and
see. So, there's still risks involved,
but those risks are hugely mitigated
nowadays. Absolutely.
>> In this modern age of commercial air
travel, do you think many of us have
lost sight of those early test pilots
and just what they achieved?
>> Yes. Because we have these shiny,
beautiful, safe vehicles, our airliners,
and we just get into them and off we go
on holiday. And what's gone into that
science? Yes, absolutely. These are
heroes. remember every school boy in in
the United Kingdom would know who the
latest test pilot was.
>> Well, today you're going to give me a
chance
>> to fly next to you, Alan, showing me the
ropes, seeing what kind of a pilot I
might make in one of your very beautiful
looking simulators.
>> Yes, absolutely. I'll [music] be
delighted to show you what the thing can
do,
>> he says with a smile on his face.
>> Do you have a sick bag?
>> Well, you know what's coming, don't you?
[laughter]
>> Come on, let's go have a look.
>> Very good.
The pioneers of aviation during the 20th
century took untold risks. At Farra
alone, nine test pilots died in the name
of science.
I'm certainly not brave enough to follow
in a test pilot's footsteps. So, with
the use of modern technology, I'm going
to fly a Boeing 747 simulator, which is
used in the training of pilots today. I
have no idea quite what I'm letting
myself in for.
Okay, Jules. Uh, this is my colleague,
Paul.
>> Hi, Paul. Nice to see you. Hi,
>> Jules. Nice to meet you.
>> I can't believe I'm sat in the pilot
seat of a jumbo jet. This is a boyhood
dream come true. Thankfully, I'm not
risking my life or indeed theirs, but I
have got a lot to learn. Paul, are we
ready to go?
>> We're ready to go. Right, then let's go.
>> Control column here.
>> Yep.
>> That's to descend.
That's to climb left and right. Very
small positive corrections. It's very,
very sensitive. As we go down the
runway, um, I'll tell you to rotate.
When you do rotate, just slowly pull
back. Try and put the center of the
screen, that little square dot in the
middle, into the magenta cross.
>> Should we give it a go? Now, setting
takeoff thrust.
>> This is astonishing. I've always wanted
to see this.
>> And rotate slowly back.
And we're in the air.
>> We're in the air. Gear up. Gear up.
Bring the the nose right up into the
cross.
>> Take some of the pressure off you and
set the autopilot. Take your hands off
the control column. So now we're flying.
>> Now we're flying. The aircraft is flying
itself.
>> Now at the moment, everything's calm and
organized and everybody's back there
enjoying their flight, I hope. Getting
into the movies and the drinks and so
on.
>> Yes.
>> What could possibly go wrong?
>> Should we have a look, shall we?
>> He's looking.
>> What you fancy, Alan?
>> Well, I get to play God. And what we're
going to simulate is a failure of one of
the autoflight systems where you as the
pilot are going to rescue the day.
>> Well, with with some help.
>> So, if I disconnect the auto throttle
>> y
>> close the thrust levers, we'll just let
the autopilot do its thing. So, we've
got our first warning, which is auto
throttle disconnect. You can see the
caution light comes on.
>> So, the aircraft is losing power.
>> It is losing power now. We're only at
idle thrust. The thrust levers are
closed. Yeah. And what's happening now
is the aircraft is
>> putting the nose up, trying to increase
the lift from the wings.
>> So, it's doing that.
>> And as you can see here on the
artificial horizon, in fact, the nose is
slowly coming up. We're going into the
yellow area here, which is the buffer
warning, which is a warning of an
oncoming stall. There's our second
warning, which is the air speed low
warning. Now, now you can feel the stall
coming on.
>> Starting to shake.
>> Shake. Starting to shake.
>> Y. And then
the final bit that we have is the stick
shaker which comes in and from that we
recover. So push the nose forward.
>> Well, that gets your attention. Whoa.
Wow. Okay. Yeah.
>> Bring the thrust in. Increasing speed.
Bringing the lift back into the wings.
[music]
>> Keep heading down.
>> Keep heading down and then slowly slowly
but not too fast because you'll bring it
back into a stall.
>> So you're pushing it back through the
curve, aren't you?
>> Yeah. You're pushing it back in to
create the lift.
>> Yeah. And we've lost 1,000 ft in that
action just to just to recover the
aircraft and bring it back into a flying
state. We level off at around about
7,000 ft.
>> Yeah.
>> And the aircraft's flying again.
>> We have successfully got ourselves
airborne. We've overcome the challenge
of what could have been a very
catastrophic in-flight scenario.
Should we go and land?
>> Yes.
>> I can't wait to see that runway open up.
[laughter]
>> You have control.
>> Clear land. 27 left. Jules 01.
>> We are coming into land at Heathrow and
I'm seeing what is a very familiar
airport to me.
>> In a completely different light 400 ft.
Here we go. There's the terminal
buildings. There's runway nicely and
little
>> 300.
>> Now look out the window. Look down the
end of the runway.
>> Yep.
>> Don't let the end of the runway sink or
rise. Just keep it where it is in the
window. Y
>> and you'll line perfectly.
>> 100.
>> 100 ft.
>> Yep.
>> 50 ft. The thrust starts to come up.
30 30
>> touches the runway. Speed breaks
>> and we're down.
>> Deployed and we're down. Still flying
though. Still doing 140 knots. Slowing
down. Slowing down. Slowing down.
>> And I have control.
>> Well, captains, both of you,
>> thank you very much indeed, Paul.
>> Thank you,
>> Alan. Thank you.
>> Very welcome. And it's nice to know that
we're all that bit safer thanks to the
work that you do and these remarkable
simulators.
>> Indeed.
>> As well as testing the limits of
aircraft at Farra, they were also
interested in testing the stamina and
the endurance of the pilots if you like
the human factor. In 1945, the Institute
of Aviation Medicine known as I am moved
in.
>> The IM's role was twofold. Firstly to
investigate the effects of the various
stresses encountered in aviation on
pilots and secondly to assist the Royal
Aircraft Establishment in developing new
items of air crew equipment uh to
protect pilots against those stresses.
The I am pushed the human body to its
limits. From geforce, the stress of heat
and cold, noise and vibration to spatial
disorientation and human error, every
possible scenario was tested. And when
they ran out of volunteers and pilots,
the scientists found themselves in the
firing line. The scientists at Farra
used themselves as experimental subjects
and two of the most famous regard Roland
Winfield and the snatch experiments
which were designed to pick reagents up
from the ground without having to land
an aircraft. So the snatch had to be
clean and then they had to be wound up
into an aircraft safely without losing
them off the end of the rope. The other
famous one at Farra involved Edgar
Pasque who was an anist.
And this involved making himself
unconscious and being thrown into a
swimming pool wearing different types of
life preserver to test which were most
effective. You couldn't be a good human
physiologist unless you regarded your
body and those of your colleagues as
something to be used and if necessary
used up was absolutely true.
>> [music]
>> The I am became a worldleading center
for aviation medicine research.
In 1994, the government combined their
resources and the center moved, forming
the new Defense Evaluation and Research
Agency of Human Sciences. Today, it's
based at RAF Henllo. But the testing
hasn't stopped.
The business of aviation medicine hasn't
really changed much over the years
because the same hazards still exist in
the flight environment. So pilots still
need to understand about the the dangers
of hypoxia or low oxygen levels. When
one gets hypoxic, there is less oxygen
being delivered to the body's organs.
And uh when one does get hypoxic, brain
function tends to diminish.
Traditionally what we do is give people
their hypoxia experience in a hyperbaric
chamber such as this one. Uh what we
would do is sit them in here and
simulate taking them to altitude by
sucking out uh some of the air that's in
here. We now moved away from this type
of uh training and we do far more uh
groundbased hypoxia training. In that
situation uh we keep the pressure the
same and it's the percentage of oxygen
in the air that we decrease. Pilots will
be flying a flight simulator and doing
flight related tasks whereas non-pilots
will be doing uh simple cognitive tasks
such as sums. These things uh bring out
the symptoms of uh hypoxia such as
tingling of the fingers around the mouth
and some people even experience changes
in mood and uh get develop a euphoria.
So if we can give our pilots and our air
crews the training that they understand
what some of the symptoms are, whether
it be of hypoxia or spatial
disorientation or things that they
should do if they're in high G
performing aircraft, then it's it's
really all about delivering that
training so they can prevent getting
into adverse situations in the air and
therefore reduce the risk to their life.
The work undertaken by the Institute of
Aviation Medicine meant the human factor
wouldn't limit any technical advances in
aircraft design. Pilots today can take
their aircraft to incredible heights at
incredible speeds while performing
deathdeying maneuvers. But throughout
aviation history, some of these advances
came at a high price.
One aircraft that found itself grounded
[music] after only 2 years of service
was the Dehavland Comet. It looked to
take the world by storm [music]
until two unexplained midair disasters
rocked the aviation industry.
The first flight of the Ghavlin comet in
1952 in passenger service was a huge
step forward for the passengers. It h
haveved the journey times to the far
east and to South Africa. It allowed the
passengers to travel in a pressurized
cabin for the first time that was
comfortable that allowed them to fly at
high altitude above the turbulence and
it really made a step forward for
passengers.
A year after entering service, problems
started to appear. Two fatal crashes
[music] during routine flights grounded
the entire fleet and Farra's scientists
were called in to investigate. One of
the pieces of work that Farra did was to
take a fuselage just like this one and
to put it into a water tank. By putting
it into a water tank and pressurizing
the water inside the cabin, it simulated
the pressurization of the cabin as it
would go through a normal flight. By
doing that, they could do a flight in 10
to 15 minutes and really accelerate the
wear on the cabin that you would see in
normal service. And sometime in June
1954, the aircraft that was being tested
broke. And when they drained the water
out and investigated the fuselage, they
found out that there was a big crack
growing [music] from the forward port
escape hatch.
The constant pressurization and
depressurization of the [music] plane's
fuselage during flights had forced
little defects in the skin to grow and
expand, which over time produced large
gaping holes. This is a typical piece of
comet skin. It shows how thick it was,
just under a millimeter thick around the
windows. And it shows the rivet holes
have been punched in. And it's from
these rivet holes that little defects
grew. And just like you can see here,
the constant flexing of the fuselage
with pressurization and depressurization
caused cracks to grow. And it's these
cracks that grew and grew during each
flight until the aircraft crashed. The
dehavlin comet became a successful
design, flying for 60 years with the
military as the Nimrod. And the lessons
learned at Farra meant that windows
changed in their design, that the skins
of aircraft became thicker, and we
designed with fatigue in mind. This put
Farmer at the forefront of aviation
research and also meant that air travel
was much safer than it was before. The
legacy of air crash investigations lives
on in Farra today. The modern air
accident investigation teams are based
on the outskirts of the modern airfield.
Every year their teams according to
research air crashes, not least the loss
of flight MH17 that was lost over the
Ukraine in July 2014. So the name
Farborra hasn't just become synonymous
with flight, but crucially with flight
safety.
The Royal Aircraft Establishment at
Farra's contribution to the development
of world aviation is endless. No other
aeronautical site in Britain has had
such an unbroken record [music] of
involvement in research.
The RAE materials department had joined
the race to find the holy grail of
material sciences. How best to combine
the strength of metal with the lightness
of plastic. And in 1963, three RE
scientists came up with the answer.
>> Peter, carbon fiber has come an awful
long way since the early 1960s.
>> It has indeed. Indeed. What is it now
that makes it so different to what it
was then?
>> It's it's our knowledge of it and how to
use it and how to process it. It's moved
out of, if you like, the laboratory into
everyday use because we understand it.
The NCC is about accelerating
innovation, taking it from the
laboratory and and really helping
industry work out how to use these
materials, how to manufacture them, how
to make them safe and take advantage of
them, if you like, all at the same time.
>> What makes it so applicable to aviation?
It's fundamentally the the the strength
to weight ratio. You get the same
strength in a very very light piece of
structure. The lighter you make the
aircraft, the more passengers you can
carry, the less fuel you use, all those
sort of things that make aviation more
and more efficient. And and it is a
phenomenal material. If you look at this
here, the strength of weight, you can
feel how light that is, but you just
feel how how incredibly stiff and strong
that is.
>> How important a discovery was this?
>> Incredibly. Modern aviation just would
not be the same without it. There's no
way we would be flying aircraft the
distance we are with the economics we do
with the emissions that have been
achieved nowadays.
>> And of course now it's creeping into
everyday life, particularly in sport,
from boats to bicycles to bats. What are
you doing with it now?
>> What are we doing? Well, let me just
show you some of the advanced technology
that's being developed for the future.
>> Okay. So now I'd like to show you the
real cutting edge of what we do with
carbon fiber. Here we're using robots to
lay up carbon uh into into molds to make
products. I'd like to introduce you to
Ben from GKM. Ben.
>> Hello Ben.
>> Hi there.
>> Nice to see you. How are you?
>> Nice to meet you.
>> Wow. This is um quite impressive. Which
part of an aircraft is this?
>> Um so this is actually a winglet skin uh
which is a lower skin of a a winglet
component which sits on the end of an
aircraft wing.
>> And what does it do for the aircraft?
>> Well, this this effectively makes the
wing appear like it's longer to the
aerodynamics. unwinds the air flow,
makes the aircraft more efficient, uses
less fuel, less CO2 emissions, but
without occupying any more space. So
when it comes to moving the air aircraft
around the airport, it doesn't occupy
bigger space. They don't need bigger
gates and that sort of thing. So you're
getting more efficiency without the
without the impact of the airfield.
>> How much is aviation taking on carbon
fiber? How much of an aircraft can be
made from carbon fiber?
>> Well, today about just over 50% of the
current breed of aircraft are made out
of carbon fiber. that's progressively
grown from the early applications in the
in the ' 70s which were just small parts
and as we've become better at
understanding how to use the material,
how to make some of the the super
critical parts like the wings and and
and other parts have the confidence in
using the material then then that's
progressively found its way across the
aircraft. I suppose Ben when we come
back to that issue of weight so critical
to aviation super critical yes
>> how much weight does this add to a
standard aircraft wing? Um, as we know,
carbon fiber itself is a a fairly light
material for the strength properties it
gives you. Um, you could probably
imagine something this size, what it
would weigh and how heavy it would be if
it was made from aluminium, for example.
So, I don't know if you would just want
to grab it and you'll see how exactly
how light this is.
>> I'm going to break it.
>> I hope not. [laughter]
>> So, there you go.
>> That's incredible.
>> Yeah, that's lighter than a surfboard,
isn't it? Indeed.
>> That's ridiculous. Well, like I say,
when you consider how strong it needs to
be, it's quite incredible the weight we
can actually get it down to to still
perform as it should do on the aircraft.
>> Ben, what exactly are these robots
doing?
>> Um, so these robots are actually laying
down individual toes of carbon fiber.
They go into different orientations.
This is what gives us the strength of
the component by just different
directions and different layers of this
material. The reason we use this
material is because it's very strong in
tension. So, if you wanted to pull on
the end of that, we never break it. We
both fall over and look silly.
>> It's not a Christmas cracker, is it?
>> It's not quite.
>> It's not going anywhere. Hope they go
bang. Anyway, um when you look at it in
the crossways direction,
>> you can tease it apart really easily.
>> It's actually very fragile, which is why
we need the different layers of
orientation to get the strengths we
desire.
>> Well, it's been a fascinating
opportunity to see behind the scenes and
to see modern manufacturing, as you say,
at its absolute best. And certainly next
time I go on holiday, I should look
again at the winglets out of the window.
And I'll think of you, Ben. Thanks very
much. [laughter]
The groundbreaking work carried out by
the scientists at Farra in developing
the strength of carbon fiber allows
designers to juggle the demands of
aerodynamics, fuel savings, and engine
noise. In today's world of mass
commercial flight, making planes bigger
and faster is essential. The NCC is a
fascinating facility. This is just one
of the ovens they use to finalize the
process of turning carbon fiber into
aircraft components. But when you think
about the 50 years or so that have
passed since this material was first
invented, trying to keep up with the
huge advances in aviation technology can
feel like quite a daunting task. But I
think one thing is for sure, carbon
fiber is here to stay until, of course,
they come up with something even lighter
and even stronger.
One of the key tools in aviation testing
is the wind tunnel. This massive 24 ft
tunnel was built in the 1930s and could
simulate winds of over a 100 miles an
hour, allowing scientists to analyze and
improve the aerodynamics of aircraft.
And with the development of the jet
engine, a whole new spectrum of speed
was unlocked, supersonic flight.
When the British and French aviation
industries combined to develop a new
supersonic passenger airliner in the
1950s and60s, where else will they come
but Farra to test their design?
Sadly, I was never lucky [music] enough
to take a trip on a Concord. These days,
all of those that did fly have now been
grounded, and without exception, they're
all preserved in museums throughout
[music] the world. To take a closer look
at what makes this aircraft so special,
I've come up to the Imperial War Museum
at Duxford. And this aircraft is
particularly unique because this was one
of the first.
The supersonic passenger airliner first
flew in 1969
and entered service in 1976.
British Airways and Air France built 20
Concords in all with 14 making the
transatlantic trip from Europe to
America.
I think part of the beauty of Concord is
in its perceived simplicity. But do not
be fooled. On a conventional aircraft
wing, for example, there are up to 50
moving parts. On Concord, there are only
six. There they are either side of those
two enormous Olympus engines.
>> [music]
>> When you get up close to Concord, you
realize that with very few exceptions,
there isn't really a straight line on
it. But it's the wing and this leading
edge of the wing that really tells the
story. It's a complicated series of
mathematical equations that have created
curve upon curve. In particular, this
twist and droop running right down there
to the wing tip. What it means is that
Concord had incredible stability at low
speeds, but low enough drag to go
supersonic. It is an essay in air flow.
But to be honest, to really understand
it, you need a physics degree.
[music]
Just when you think you've mastered the
simplicity of Concord, you come into the
cockpit and you realize that you've
learned absolutely nothing. It is a maze
of dials and buttons and I suppose
really goes to the heart of the
development of this aircraft.
>> Well, it does. I mean, this was a
pre-production model. Uh there were two
prototypes and then there were two
pre-production models which were used
for testing. This was the British
pre-production model. And am I right in
saying that this was the fastest Concord
that ever flew?
>> Yes, it was. This one flew at 2.23 Mac.
>> 2.23 Mac. So in pounds and pence, that's
1,450
mph.
>> Isn't that astonishing?
>> Absolutely astonishing.
>> I mean, that's virtually London's New
York in 2 hours.
>> Two and a half certainly. [laughter] But
but yes, I mean, you certainly would
have arrived in New York 2 or 3 hours
before you taken off at Keith.
>> That's incredible, isn't it? But in many
ways, David, Concord challenged and
broke many of the accepted parameters
for the operation of aircraft.
>> Well, it did. It was very experimental
in many ways. Um, obviously they there
had been supersonic fighter jets and
things like that that went before, but
transferring that technology to an
airliner that could carry 100 people
with great reliability was a whole
different ball game.
>> But it was operating in extremes of cold
and heat.
>> Indeed, it was. It would take off from
Heathrow on a cold winter's day in
negative temperatures and by the time it
was flying at 60,000 ft at 1400 mph, it
was probably 120 130° centigrade. So the
fuselage expanded and expanded by around
about 9 9 in in old units.
>> 9 in. So almost what 25 cmters.
>> Absolutely. I suppose one of the most um
headline grabbing features of Concord,
apart from its incredible speed, was the
nose and the fact that the nose would
move. Why was that such an important
thing to create?
>> Well, uh basically because the wing is
designed for supersonic flight, as the
plane slows down to come into land, it
has to take up a fairly steep angle,
which we're all very familiar with.
>> It fled hugely, didn't as it landed.
>> Absolutely. Right. Well, of course, the
pilots couldn't see anything. I mean,
they were, you know, they were facing
the sky. So the droop nose was the the
solution. This particular aircraft,
interestingly enough, uh because it was
the first time that they we had this um
visor that you could see out of the
visor lowers first and the nose goes
down to 5° and then ours goes down to 17
12. When they then started to get the
commercial airline pilots involved and
they started to fly it and test it out,
they said, "Well, we we can't see where
we're going." like the bonnet of a car.
They had nothing at the front to look at
when they were trying to land.
>> I mean, I sort of take the point. There
isn't a huge area of view there, is
there?
>> There's not a lot of a view, but all
that falls away, of course, when you're
coming in to land, but they hadn't got
this front of the bonnet. So, they
decided that rather than 17 1/2°, 12
would be better. You know, this aircraft
in particular to me is something of an
old friend. It's one of the very first
aircraft I ever saw here at Duxford as a
young kid of about seven years old. And
here I am still coming back to enjoy it.
>> Glad to hear it. The Concord bug has
bitten.
>> Yes,
>> David. Thank you very much.
>> Pleasure.
>> After the tragic crash in Paris in 2000
and dwindling passenger numbers, the
Concord fleet was retired in 2003,
ending commercial supersonic flight. But
failures in planes don't stop [music]
development. They just make engineers
and scientists more determined to
succeed. And who knows how aviation will
develop in the future.
The history of Farra will be forever
linked with the history of British
aviation. But there can be few other
airfields that have had such a
longlasting or indeed global impact on
the story of international aerospace
engineering. The RAE and all the other
research institutions that were once
based here have now long gone and Farra
is now simply an airport. But thanks to
history and preservation, the stories
and the lives that surrounded those
early pioneers of flight will never be
forgotten.
For over a century, the legendary tales
that have surrounded our great British
airfields have inspired generations of
people, including me. Which is why I am
on a personal mission to cross the UK to
visit some of our most important
airfields to understand not just about
their contribution to our past, but
importantly, how many of them have
helped define our future. From the UK's
first [music] flight through to
groundbreaking innovations such as
carbon fiber and the jet engine and the
extraordinary [music] efforts spent on
preserving our aviation heritage. Join
me as I explore the story of the
airfields that have helped [music] shape
Britain and the world.
I'm here at RAF Biggan Hill, one of the
most famous airfields of the Second
World War. Big on the bump, as it was
known, became synonymous with the Battle
of Britain, the aerial campaign that
thwarted Hitler's attempts at invasion
back in the summer of 1940. The pilots
that took off from this runway faced
overwhelming odds, but in overcoming
them, they wrote themselves into the
history books.
>> Two threshold QF [music] 978. We're on
runway 03.
>> The geography here at Vigan Hill ensured
the creation of an airfield back in 1917
towards the end of the First World War.
And its unique characteristics have
meant that nearly a century later,
[music] it's still a very busy place.
>> Back is correct. Next, report ready to
taxi.
>> Bob, very nice to see you, sir.
>> Hello.
>> Admiring an airfield that you have
studied for years.
>> Yes, I have. So tell us why was Big and
Hill founded here?
>> It started life as a wireless testing
station and they came across this field
here 80 acres absolutely massive. It was
650 ft above sea level but it was a
perfect place and they perfected
communication between aircraft in flight
and the ground through this amazing new
technology.
>> Hence bigger on the bump. pick them on
the bump and upturn the saucepan. But as
they came into land, there was a little
hill and they used to stick their noses
in the air over the other side and it
became known as the bump. And I guess
its role in the first world war really
was the kind of precursor to the second
world war when Big Hill really does earn
its wings as it were.
>> Well, it soon became a senior sector
airfield. It uh became the most famous
fighter station not only in in the
country but in the world. More than
1,400
enemy aircraft shot down. There was a
ring of fighter stations around London,
but this was the strongest link
defending the southern approaches.
In the late 1920s and early 1930s, Bigan
Hill was given a much needed revamp, the
provision of new hangers in these e-
pens to protect aircraft and their
ground crews against the possibility of
air attack. And all of that, of course,
was just as well because the clouds were
gathering [music] over Europe as war
loomed on the horizon.
In 1935,
news reached Britain that Hitler was
rumored to have a death ray using radio
waves to destroy towns and cities. So,
the Aeronautical Research Committee
asked radio engineer Robert Watson Watt
to explore creating [music] a death ray
for Britain specifically to be used
against aircraft. Watson Watt quickly
proved the death ray idea to be
impossible and suggested that perhaps
radio waves might be of more use in
detecting and tracking enemy aircraft
uniform
your own navigation to position 10 and
then NATO.
>> At its most simple terms, the primary
radar works by emitting a large pulse of
radio energy. It bounces off the metal
in the aircraft and it returns to the
radar sensor. Because we know how long
that takes to to happen and we know
which direction the signal was being
aimed, we can tell the range of the
aircraft and how far it is away from the
radar head. That then developed even
further so that we can interrogate the
flight management computer for certain
data. And we can now tell the intended
heading of the aircraft and its selected
flight level. That in itself provides a
huge safety benefit to us because we can
automatically check that against the
clearance we provided the aircraft so
that we can take early intervention if
it's necessary.
Today, the National Air Traffic Services
known as NATS control the UK's radar
system. [music]
They handle over 2 million flights a
year and over 220 million passengers in
UK airspace, controlling both civil and
military aircraft. report 37.
>> If we didn't have radar, we really are
reliant on the aircraft to report their
position. And really with the number of
aircraft that we have to maintain and
keep in the air at any one point in
time, that just wouldn't be a practical
way and there would just be so many
delays. It would be uh truly awful. But
back in the 1930s, radar was in its
infancy and RAF Big and Hill needed all
the help it could get defending London
against the approaching Germans. The
terrifying effectiveness of the German
air force had become all too apparent
during the Spanish Civil War. And here
in Britain, there is a renewed urgency
to put this new technology to good use.
Between 1937 and 1939, radio masts, just
like the one behind me, were put up all
along Britain's coastline. It was the
world's first air defense system. They
called [music] it chain home.
Well, Ally, it is amazing what you find
lying around the Essex countryside.
>> Absolutely, Jo. You find all kinds of
different things, including a 360oot
radar tower.
>> And where was this one originally cited?
>> It came from Canuden, which is near near
South End, about 25 miles from where we
stand now.
>> Well, the best view of it got to be from
over there.
>> Absolutely.
Well, Andy, there's no getting away from
the impressive nature of the Chain Home
array, but just exactly what was it and
how did it work?
>> Chain home was the United Kingdom's air
defense radar system in the Second World
War. It was designed and developed
during the middle to late 1930s. And the
original station would have consisted of
three or four of these huge 360 foot
towers separated by about 100 feet and
between them between the cantalvered
platforms would have been slung wire
antenna arrays. So the whole of the east
coast of the UK was pinpointed with
these antennas all the way along.
Somewhere beyond us over there would
have been four wooden towers 240 foot
high and they held the receive dipoles.
This was a pulse system. So a pulse of
RF would be transmitted from one of the
curtain arrays slung between the
transmit towers and it would flood light
the area in front of the radar up to 200
miles away. And then the receivers would
pick up the very very tiny signal that's
been reriated reflected from the target.
>> So it gave a sense of direction and
height.
>> It gave direction and height. Yes. And
it meant that we could scramble our
aircraft and they could be in the right
place at the right time.
>> Could it tell you how many aircraft were
in the air? not on its own but a trained
operator could be able to have a good
estimate of the of the number of uh of
aircraft by looking at the size of the
return signal.
>> Its great champion was Dowing. Tell us
about the Dowing system.
>> Well, what Dowing did was he he looked
at the uh at the problems of air defense
as a whole. So the whole system um of
air defense from the anti-aircraft guns
to the search lights was all integrated
into this whole dowing system which
meant nothing worked on its own. It was
all if you like orchestrated from uh
from a central place.
The dowing system was the key instrument
of war in Fighter Command's armory.
Denied [music] the enemy the element of
surprise. Air Chief Marshall Hugh Dowing
developed a series of reporting chains.
Information was sent from the chain home
to Fighter Command who would then in
turn relay details to the operation
sectors like Big and Hill. They would
then scramble the airfields and the
squadrons.
>> Now, these do look like pretty juicy
targets uh for the Luftwafer. How many
of these stations were destroyed in a
test?
>> They did try and destroy them, but
they're mostly air. So bombs landing
other than a direct hit did very little
damage. Not until the middle of the war
did they even realize that it was a
radar system. When we think of the
Battle of Britain, we tend to of course
focus on the famous few that Churchill
describes, the fighter pilots. But
actually, it's the Backroom boys who
came up with systems like this that we
really have to thank.
>> That's right. I mean the the fighter
pilots wouldn't have been in the right
place had it have not been for radar
because we were so outnumbered without
chain home we would almost certainly
have lost the battle of Britain
before World War II interception rates
of 30 to 50% [music] were considered
excellent. Now with the dowing system in
place fighter command achieved well over
80%.
Without chain home, Big and Hill's
organized defense of London would have
been virtually impossible.
The effective development and
implementation of radar could not have
come soon enough. Hitler's invasion of
Europe had proved to be a resounding
success, and his next objective was to
knock Britain out of the war.
When in 1940 it became evident that
Churchill wouldn't surrender, Hitler
tasked his military to draw up plans for
an invasion of the UK. What they came up
with was cenamed Operation Seaine. There
was a great deal of optimism in the
higher echelons of the German armed
forces that a successful invasion of
Britain could take place, especially in
the army and in the air force, the the
Luftwaffer. But there was a greater
reluctance to mount an invasion by the
German Navy. Grand Admiral Rder, the
commander-in-chief of the German Navy,
realized that because most of his
surface fleet had been destroyed or
knocked out during the Norwegian
campaign that had been fought between
April and June 1940, he was very worried
that the Navy wouldn't be able to escort
the invading forces over the channel
successfully. By August 1940, a large
number of vessels, including 2,000
barges, had been assembled on the
Belgian and French coasts. But to launch
an invasion on Britain, Hitler needed to
control the English Channel. To do this,
Germany needed control of the air, and
that meant taking on the Royal Air
Force. The Germans were going to use 13
divisions in the initial assault on
southern Britain. The objective being
London, of course, and eventually the
invading force would have total 39
divisions, including 15 to 17,000 men,
but also including [music] three Panza
divisions in the initial assault, each
of which had about 250 tanks. So, it was
quite a formidable force. I mean the
British, one must remember, had lost a
lot of equipment in France. The men
[music] had come back with their rifles,
but very little else. A lot of guns,
tanks had been left behind, and Britain
was really [music] very, very denuded of
armament.
Hitler's air force entered the battle
with around 1,300 bombers and dive
bombers and about 900 single engine and
300 twin engine fighters, significantly
more than the 600 that RAF Fighter
Command had available at the time. The
Germans had a very healthy respect for
the Royal Air Force and they realized
that the full resources of the Royal Air
Force hadn't been thrown into the Battle
of France as the French government
pleaded with Churchill to do so because
Churchill was very conscious of the fact
that the Royal Air Force Fighter Command
was needed to defend [music] Britain.
Hitler says in his directive that it was
vital that the German Air Force destroys
the English air force and he calls it
the English air force, not the Royal Air
Force. It was vital to knock the RAF
out.
[music]
By July 1940, the stage was set for the
first major campaign between two rival
air forces. Now, the Germans, of course,
had their bomber fleet and the highly
regarded ME109 Meshaspit fighter, but in
some regards, well, the RAF held all the
aces. two aircraft that would become
synonymous with the exploits during the
Battle of Britain, the Huracan
and the Spitfire.
>> [music]
>> Well done, Paul. Well, you know, my day
just gets better and better. Look at it.
We're on Big and Hill airfield. We've
got three beautiful aircraft to look at.
The Huracan, of course, and these two
Spitfires. I mean, this really is the
story of Big and Hill. This aircraft,
>> it is. Yeah, it's iconic. I mean, Big
and Hill's an iconic airfield, but the
Spitfire is really the icon of the
Battle of Britain, if you like.
>> Well, come on, show me around. I can't
wait to get up close the design of it.
These elliptical wings very much an icon
again of the period of the 1930s and yet
have produced the most beautiful
airplane.
>> Well, that's the that's the real thing
about this. It is it's an iconic shape,
but it's really just practicality. It
was the most efficient shape they knew
of at the time. And Mitchell, who
designed it, said, "I don't care what
shape it is as long as it covers the
guns." Little did he know he was
creating not just a design icon and a
beautiful aircraft but a war-winning
solution. When I talked to pilots who
flew these during the war, they say it
was really an extension if you like of
themselves.
>> Oh yeah. Many pilots have commented that
you used to strap the airplane on like
you were wearing it and uh you go off
and fight. You're not even conscious of
the airplane when you're fighting with
it. Fingertip movements on the controls.
It's so responsive. You think about
turning, it's already turning for you.
For me, the shape of this airplane is so
beautiful that we'd already won the war
on style. You know, with airplanes that
looked and sounded like this, you we
couldn't have lost.
>> Well, you talk about sound. That of
course comes from the famous Merlin
engine. And there's a beautiful example
of it just over here all uncovered for
us. It's a ludicrously complicated
looking thing. How did that compare to
the enemy machines? There's the measure
smmith in particular.
>> Uh the Meshasmid was a little bit faster
in level flight. It had a better rate of
climb and a steeper climb angle so it
could get itself out of trouble. But it
also had the technique of diving. You a
measure smith could dive away from a
Spitfire. The Spitfire trying to pursue
would cough and cut out because of the
design of the carburetor.
>> Was that ever overcome?
>> It was overcome in a way actually a very
simple device like a a washer that was
inserted in the carburetor stopped all
the fuel moving to the other side of the
float chamber. Uh that that was a
temporary solution.
>> But many pilots talked about the
maneuverability of the Spitfire over the
Meshmit. What was it about the Spitfire
that gave it that edge?
>> It it it was slightly more maneuverable
than the 109. Certainly, it was a very
complicated machine, but very advanced.
>> The first prototype of the Supermarine
Spitfire flew in 1936, and [music] it
was placed into production in 1938.
At the outset of the Battle of Britain,
only 19 squadrons had Spitfires compared
to 30 armed with Huracans. The
Supermarine's elliptical wing design
made it fast and maneuverable in a dog
fight. The Rolls-Royce Merlin engine
gave it a speed of over 350 mph.
It had a wingspan of over 36 ft and a
maximum speed of 408 mph.
Its firepower developed from eight
Browning machine guns to four powerful
20 mm cannons.
Overall, the Spitfire squadrons were
responsible for shooting down 521
enemy aircraft,
an average of 27 per squadron.
Well, we've talked about that sense that
pilots could virtually wear their
aircraft. I know we're not going to get
a chance to fly in one today, which I
would love to do, but can I have a sit
inside?
>> Certainly can.
>> Which one? This one.
>> This one over here.
I have been looking forward to this for
a long time.
>> You've already got the Spitfire Grin.
You're not even in it.
>> Ah, you see the Spitfire Grin.
>> Oh, yes.
>> Well, that's a given.
>> This is just beautiful. What's the best
way?
>> Uh, the way to get in is to hold on to
the armor plate here and the windscreen
frame that you've got there. Y
>> stand on this ledge and then stand on
the seat.
>> Okay, here we go. My first
>> dive into a Spitfire.
And then just pop my feet in.
>> That's it. Yeah. Put your feet down
there where the rudder pedals are.
>> Oh, you talk about that Spitfire grin.
It's a glow that kind of flows through
you.
>> Oh, yeah. Yeah. And it happens to just
about everyone their first time and the
second time and the third time.
>> Now, you've been involved in restoring
these aircraft for many years, Paul. How
many man hours did it take to build one?
>> To build one originally, uh, just over
15,000 man hours.
>> 15,000. and keeping them in the air. In
particular, at stations like this one at
Big and Hill, which were under such
heavy attack during those heady days of
the Battle of Britain must have been an
uphill battle.
>> It was a roundthe-clock process. They
they they never stopped. And you'd
always get the the chief engineer on the
squadron saying, you know, I want these
serviceable for tomorrow morning
>> regardless. Yeah. Regardless.
>> And they they move heaven and earth to
get as many airplanes up as possible.
But of course, the Spitfire, although
the icon of the Battle of Britain, was
outnumbered, not by the enemy in many
respects, but by the Huracan. More
Huracans flew in the Battle of Britain
than almost any other aircraft.
>> That's true. Yeah, there were more
Huracans. In fact, twothirds of the
fighter force were huracans.
Correspondingly, they got more kills
than the Spitfire. Um they were sent
after the bombers in a lot of cases
because they were very good for shooting
with very stable uh and could take a lot
of punishment because they were uh
fabric construction down the back of the
fuselage especially.
>> Now I'm going to chance my luck today.
I've already had a chance to get into a
Spitfire. Can we have a look at that
Huracan too?
>> Certainly can.
The first prototype of the Hawker
Huracan was introduced in 1935 [music]
and went into production in 1937.
It was the first single wing or
monoplane RAF fighter and in total
14,583
were manufactured.
With a wingspan of 40 foot and a
Rolls-Royce Merlin 3 12cylinder liquid
cooled engine, it was the first RAF
aircraft capable of a top speed in
excess of 300 mph.
The fighter plane carried an armory of
eight Browning machine guns mounted in
its wings. Although largely overshadowed
by the Spitfire, it's estimated that its
pilots were credited with 58% of all
enemy aircraft destroyed, an average of
53 per squadron.
>> So this is your Huracan.
>> This is a Huracan. And everywhere you
look on a Huracan is chunky. It's got a
great big thick wing which made it very
stable for shooting. And I love this
characteristic ribbing almost. It's this
wonderful fusion between the newer
technology at the front and the older
timber and canvas at the back.
>> It is a bit of a mixture. I mean, the
engine's the same as the Spitfire
engine, but apart from that, it's
pre-war technology. It's like a biplane
almost.
>> But how robust were these up against the
German aircraft?
>> These were very robust. But the key to
this is a bullet would go straight
through hopefully without hitting
anything important on its journey. And
you could easily repair that by just
letting a patch in.
>> Ah, yeah. didn't have to rivet or cut
metal. You literally just dope a patch
on.
>> And there was quite an important
equation between fighters being built
and fighters being lost.
>> How quick were these to make compared to
a Spitfire?
>> They were uh you could shave a third of
the time off. They're about 10,000 hours
to build.
>> Really?
>> It's hard to believe that these were
somehow perceived as less glamorous than
a Spitfire given the job they were
doing.
>> They're not as glamorous. You know,
they're fabric and wood and, you know,
they don't get the blood racing like a
Spitfire does unless you're actually
flying one. But, uh, one of one of them
has to get the glamour. One of them has
to do the work, and it's the Huracan
that's the, uh, the workhorse, should we
say.
>> If you had to choose between the two.
What's your favorite?
>> Well, I'm a Spitfire junkie, so
[laughter]
the heart rules the head on that one.
>> Yeah. I mean, I have to confess, I'm
going to put my colors on the Huracan
Mast. I love them. I love their squat
shape, and I love the fact that they
were the underdog in a way in
technological terms, but they were the
backbone of the fighter force then. But
either or, I'd have one for Christmas,
wouldn't you?
>> Couldn't have done without either of
them.
>> Spectacular though these planes are, the
experience must have been terrifying.
With the gun button set to fire, it was
every man for himself. With your own
personal survival and the fate of your
country at risk, the stakes were high.
Now, the main objective of those Lufafa
raids was to knock the RAF out of the
war. And until it was defeated, Hitler's
planned invasion would be all but
[music] impossible. Big and Hill itself
was attacked numerous times throughout
August and September of 1940, leaving
the airfield pretty much devastated, but
it never shut. And it's against that
backdrop that ground crews worked
tirelessly day and night, not just to
keep the RAF in the air, but importantly
to keep Britain in the war.
The members of the Women's Auxiliary Air
Force or WAFS as they were known played
a vital role in fighter command during
the battle. They used the huge chain
home radars to locate air raids and
report their positions as well as
plotting these reports in the control
rooms.
>> We're here in the Battle of Britain
bunker at RAF Oxbridge. We are 60 feet
underground and this is where the battle
of Britain uh was operated from was
controlled. Around this table you would
have had up to 20 members of the women's
auxiliary air force receiving
information about incoming bombers
plotting it on this map in front of us
and then helping the other RAF bases to
scramble fighters to intercept those
incoming bombers. The Battle of Britain
really was the first point at which we
were truly truly tested as a service and
as such if we were going to have any
chance of defending against incoming
attacks then as many men standing in
this room as possible had to be flying.
Uh and if that was going to be the case
then we simply had to substitute women
for men in these roles. So by the summer
of 1940, there would have been 20
women's auxiliary air force members
standing around this table doing the
jobs that only months earlier men would
have been doing.
>> 200 women worked at Big and Hill. Their
roles varied from catering and washing
pilots clothes to the more technical
side of radar operations and servicing
aircraft. Of course, very quickly, women
[music] proved that they were more than
capable of holding their tongues, of
maintaining their [music] cool under the
most intense pressure, even to the
extent that three WF who worked at Big
Hill were awarded the military medal.
Three of only six in the whole of the
war for holding to their posts under
fire when Biggin Hill became the center
of a lift buffer attack. One such W,
Elizabeth Mortimer, was serving at Big
Hill. she was operating the telephones
and came under direct fire uh on the
night of the 31st of August into the 1st
of September in particular [music]
and she held to her post and then having
finished her shift she decided that in
order to warn the returning air crew
that there might be unexloded bombs she
would run around the airfield finding
where she thought those unexloded bombs
might be and marking the sights with a
red flag. At one point, a bomb exploded
so close to her that she was blown off
her feet uh and actually remained deaf
in one ear pretty much for the rest of
her life. But she got up, dusted herself
down, and continued planting her red
flags, putting to bed the idea that
women might buckle under pressure or not
be sufficiently brave to work in this
sort of context.
>> Big and Hill was one of the first
targets in the Luftwaffer raids. Between
August 1940 and January 1941, the
airfield was attacked 12 times,
destroying barracks and workshops and
killing 39 people.
>> We did see a real revolution, albeit a
small and ongoing revolution if you
like, in the way that women were
perceived as a result of the way in
which they played their part in this
room and others around the country doing
these sorts of roles at a time when
there was simply nothing else to be
done. but to get on with it.
>> While the ground crews were busy
patching up the heavily damaged
airfields, the pilots were trying to
shoot down as many enemy bombers as
possible before they reached the
targets. But whether you were flying a
Spitfire or a Huracan, you were
completely reliant on the eight 303
Browning machine guns that each aircraft
carried. But just how effective were
they? Well, I've come here to this
rather spooky facility to find out.
Dave,
>> Jules, hello, mate.
>> This is an extraordinary place. I was
told I'd find you in here, but it's a
labyrinth.
>> It is. Yeah, it's quite a big complex.
>> And you've got the facilities to test
more or less any kind of weapon.
>> Yeah, we certainly test a lot of small
arms here anyway.
>> And that's the range.
>> How long is that?
>> The range is over 200 m long.
>> Wow. Now, what have we got at the end of
it?
>> At the end of the range, you can see
measure smith armor. It's a
representation of 5 mil, 8 mil, and 12
mil armor. Five mil on the wing spars,
eight mil on the pilot protection area,
and then 12 mil on the bulkhead.
>> Now, we've got two fascinating looking
weapons here that I recognize as a Bren
gun.
>> Yep.
>> 303.
>> Yes.
>> What are we going to do with that?
>> The brain gun's going to stand in for
the 303 um aircraft because the problem
with the the the Browning 303 aircraft
machine gun is it's air operated uh
fired remotely with a trigger on the
control column of the the spay grip. And
so to make life easier, we're going to
set it up in a tripod. And next to it
you've got a 50 caliber Browning
>> during the war. All our 50 caliber
Brownings that we actually placed on the
latter Spitfires, they were all
manufactured in the US.
>> And I suppose in many ways any student
of the Battle of Britain will recognize
that the 303 Browning was a key
component. But just how good was it?
>> It was a very good reliable machine gun
from the early days when they ironed out
um the the development from the American
one and made the British Browning
machine gun. It was very very good. Its
only problem was the Germans up armored
and they'd already got a more powerful
machine gun in their own aircraft and
that was its limitation.
>> So was the Messmith 1100 better armed
than a Spitfire or a hurricane during
the battle of
>> Britain? It was. Yeah, it was. It was it
was better armed, the pilot had better
armor and and the aircraft overall had
more armor than the Spitfire or the
Huracan for that matter. So really and
truly, the the 303 really had to do a
lot of work, whereas the German aircraft
with their um cannons and machine gun
had to do a lot less.
>> So the idea is to see whether or not the
383 can get through any or all of those
armor.
>> That's That's right. Yeah.
>> How many rounds have we got?
>> Uh we've got quite a few.
>> Excellent. Well, this will be a really
interesting test to see how effective it
was.
>> With a tracer element at this range, we
should see some good tracer element
going down. Right then.
>> Let's see how our bin gun fares. Right.
Where's your helmet?
>> So, here. [laughter]
>> Gun is cocked [music] and live.
>> It's ready to go, Jules. Yeah. So, you
just get behind it.
>> Okay. [music]
>> Okay.
>> I'm ready to fire
>> in your own time. Go on.
Oh, there's a certainly
>> little spark at the end.
>> Oh, yeah.
>> Yeah, that's one.
>> Certainly hit.
>> Yep.
>> Yeah, that's good.
>> And keep going at that, George.
Round's complete, Dave. Absolutely
fascinating.
>> Well done. You hit the target.
>> There's not a huge kick out of of that.
You you get the sense that there isn't a
lot of weight behind the round.
>> Well, let's try something different.
Let's try the 50 caliber machine gun.
>> Now, I'm used to seeing these mounted on
the top of tanks or indeed in the waist
of flying fortresses and that sort of
thing.
>> Absolutely. It was absolutely completely
universal. The US Navy had them. The Air
Force had them. They had them on tanks.
They had them in the infantry role.
Yeah.
>> And it's still in use today.
>> And this is the ammunition.
>> That's the ammunition. Now, if you
compare that ammunition, that's exactly
the same as it was at wartime. And this
is the 303. So, you're now looking at
the size of that round compared to that
round.
>> Yeah.
>> Uh, so when we put an explosive charge
in the head, it's far more effective.
>> I never thought the day would ever come
when I'd get the chance to actually fire
a live 50 caliber,
>> but today is my lucky day, Dave.
>> Today's your lucky day. [laughter]
>> Right. Let's have a look and see what it
does to the armored plate.
>> Okay, Jules. I'm just going to let the
working parts forward, get it ready to
load.
>> Okay.
>> Okay. So, we'll just let the working
parts forward. Lock it off. And then
what we're going to do is Matt will
assist in the the loading. I'll assist
in watching where the rounds are going
and making any adjustments we need to
make.
>> Okay. Load.
>> And to think this is a 1945 wartime
dated weapon.
>> It is. Yeah. Absolutely. Goggles.
>> Very much.
>> Right.
>> Okay. So, we're going to [__] it
underhand. Yeah. Ah,
>> there you go. Okay. We're now loaded and
we're now ready to fire.
>> Short burst.
>> Short bursts. Yep.
>> Here we go then.
>> And again.
>> That is a thump.
You've just taken over the targets.
>> Most the targets
>> destroyed,
>> I think. Is there one left on the right?
>> Yes, there is.
>> I think that cloud of smoke means we've
got it.
>> Let's go and see what you actually have
done.
>> Be fascinating to see, won't it? You get
a real idea of the power of this weapon.
I mean, that's a real thump, a real thud
coming right through your body.
>> You can feel the shock wave. You could
actually feel it in the aircraft when
you're firing the cannon in the 50
caliber.
>> That's incredible. And of course, here
we are in the confines of this concrete
uh range. This the pressure wave, the
shock wave feels all the more. Right,
then let's go and have a look.
Wow. So, this is still standing. That's
rather disappointing, isn't it? Look at
that. You can certainly see the 50
caliber hole.
>> Absolutely. Yeah. You can actually see
that quite clearly. If you look at that,
you can really put your your finger
clearly through there. You see the ones
at the top? This is the tracer rounds
that we had in there.
>> These are the This is the 303 round.
>> This is the 303. And that's obviously
the tracer round, which is a lighter
round. And there you go. There's your
armor piercing. So, it's penetrated the
wing spar armor and certainly penetrated
the wing spar armor with a 50 cal.
>> There's absolutely no argument with
that.
>> No.
>> Is that the thickest plate?
>> This is the thickest plate. So, you
know, we can see that there it's just
riddled with holes
>> all the way through it.
>> It's I mean
>> this is 12 mm of frontal armor. So, you
can see there that is gone all the way
through. No problem. No problem at all.
>> I mean, never mind an aircraft. You can
see what it would do to a lightly
armored tank as well.
>> Yeah.
>> You know, it's interesting. You read
about this stuff. If you study it, you
talk to veterans, but when you see it
for yourself firsthand, it's
devastating. It's terrifying,
>> shocking. It's absolutely shocking. And
remember, all these holes come through,
bits come flying off. You then got
fragments and shards flying through the
aircraft, you know, hundreds of miles an
hour.
>> Fingers. Yeah,
>> there it goes. Well, Dave, it's been an
amazing day. a really fascinating
insight into just what these pilots were
up against and importantly what they
were armed with and how the battle began
to turn in our favor.
>> Yeah, it's amazing, isn't it, to see how
it all went round.
>> It really is. What a place. I'm glad I
wasn't the other end of one of those.
>> Absolutely.
>> You know, much of wartime Bigen Hill has
sadly disappeared, but this is a rare
survivor. It's the original dispersal
hut that pilots would have gathered in
and around playing cards, reading the
paper, trying to relax as they waited
for the call to scramble. And you have
to wonder if they were listening to the
radio here [music] on the 20th of August
1940 when Churchill speaking in the
Commons uttered those now immortal
[music] words.
Never in the field of human conflict was
so much owed by so many [music]
to so few.
>> He was of course talking about them.
At the time [music] Churchill made that
speech, the battle was still raging and
nowhere near one.
>> We're on the
ridge where the uh observer post and uh
a couple of guns were placed. The
airfield is now through the trees. This,
of course, was generally an open area
opposite to the airfield. When I was a
lad, this is where we came through
and continued on further. And the
position would have been somewhere just
along on this ridge here. I'd managed to
get into this area, which of course was
very much uh an area that people were
not allowed to come into. And it gave me
the opportunity to see something which
was really quite exceptional. I suppose
I didn't think that much of it in those
days, but nowadays one would realize
that you were in the front line of what
was going [music] on. The German
aircraft appeared coming from the
southeast and they started then to bomb
the airfield. I didn't feel frightened
to any great extent. It was excitement
at what was happening. This this was
boy's own stuff at its best. But of
course, it was a desperate time. And I
think as the months rolled on and the
blitz started and we were bombed out of
our house, three times they came along
and repaired it. And [music] three times
we had to leave, you realize this wasn't
just a game.
>> Both sides suffered heavy losses during
the Battle of Britain. In just 17 weeks,
nearly 1,900 Lufafa planes were
destroyed with over 2,600 casualties.
The RAF lost over 1100 aircraft and
suffered over 800 casualties.
>> I got told off time and time again, but
it was too exciting not to uh watch what
was going on. But of course, we were
winning, you see. And when you saw a
German aircraft fall away, you didn't
think of the people who were in it. you
just thought that's one less and we were
winning. We didn't realize the
importance of Big and Hill at that time
because Big and Hill was really the last
line of defense
um before London and the aircraft from
Big and Hill were the ones that had to
defend virtually London and so it it was
a place of great significance.
The RAF's success in the Battle of
Britain was indeed a turning point
during the dark days of 1940. But it had
given Hitler his first taste of defeat
and importantly had provided Britain and
her allies with a real sense of hope.
But however welcome that victory, it had
been bought at enormous personal cost.
Big and Hill was given the nickname the
strongest link for the role [music] it
played. However, countless others also
did their part in thwarting the
invasion. The Royal Observer Corps, the
women of the W, the Blenhan bombers who
destroyed the invasion barges to name
but a few. The chapel at Big and Hill
[music] holds many memories.
This case contains Big and Hill's book
of remembrance
and it's inscribed with the names of all
air crew who lost their lives throughout
the war flying from here.
It's currently opened on the 19th of
July 1940 and it records the fate of too
many of 141 squadron who flew defiance
during the Battle of Britain. Their rate
of attrition was so high following this
day, the squadron pretty much ceased to
exist.
But every day since the end of the war,
a new page has turned,
helping us to remember [music] all of
those who flew from here.
Well, this is known as St. George's room
here at the chapel at Big and Hill and
it commemorates in these stained glass
windows the ground crews that the pilots
held in such high regard. This one is
dedicated to ground control. Here we've
got the WS leaning over a plotting table
with a map of the south coast and above
them their controllers and in these
little panes the radar masks that key
component that really helped in the
battle of Britain. And this one is
dedicated to aircraft servicing.
Ground crews, their aircraft, and their
pilots often had a very close
relationship. Here we've got a crew
working hard to keep this particular
Spitfire in the air. Looks over under
the careful eye of a sergeant. And then
this one
is dedicated to those who packed the
parachutes. These really were people
you'd want to depend on.
You survived one of the riskiest jobs
that the war could offer any young man.
How did you do it?
>> I thank God. I suppose I I I I can't
really say much more than that. Uh
fortune was on your side. Uh and you
were very lucky. Uh and you pick out
fleeting glances, I think, is the the
best way I can describe it. And
sometimes it's the consequence of those
fleeting glances uh which sticks in your
mind. There are fleeting moments and it
all happens very quickly.
>> You visit the chapel here at Bigen Hill
regularly. Rodney, what does it mean to
you?
>> I would hate to to miss it. Uh
[groaning] and obviously the day will
come when I'll no longer be alive to
enjoy it. Uh but all the well I am uh
and I'm now 92 years of age. I'm very
lucky uh to be able to uh enjoy it.
As 1940 developed the fighter pilots
came into their own in the public
consciousness because of the battle of
Britain and for all the horrors and
dangers they faced their life was often
portrayed as glamorous. Did you ever see
that? Did you ever recognize that? Did
it inspire you? I wouldn't see it as a
glamour position. I would see it as a
worthwhile position that you were able
to do something uh and uh you were not
completely lost.
>> The Battle of Britain was the first
major campaign to be fought entirely in
the air. The conflict raged over
southern England for 3 months, involving
over 2,900 RAF aircraft. It was the
first Allied turning point of the Second
World War and a defining moment in world
history. The German plan to beat the RAF
had failed and so too had the invasion
of Great Britain.
You know, for many people as an
airfield, Big and Hill is hallowed
ground. Throughout the war, its
squadrons and its pilots of all
nationalities that were based here
destroyed over a thousand enemy
aircraft. Its personnel collected over
200 awards for gallantry and skill in
combat. But it is perhaps that summer of
1940 and its role in the Battle of
Britain itself that has enshrined its
place in the history books.
The gratitude of every home in our
islands, in our empire, and indeed
throughout the world, except in the
abodess of the guilty, goes out to the
British airmen, who undaunted by odds,
unwaried in their constant challenge and
mortal nature,
are turning the tide of the world war by
their prowess and by their devotion.
>> [music]
>> For over a century, the legendary tales
that have surrounded our great British
airfields have inspired generations of
people, including me. Which is why I am
on a personal mission to cross the UK to
visit some of our most important
airfields to understand not just about
their contribution to our past, but
importantly [music] how many of them
have helped define our future. From the
UK's first flight through to
groundbreaking innovations such as
carbon fiber and the jet engine and the
extraordinary efforts spent on [music]
preserving our aviation heritage. Join
me as I explore the story of the
airfields that have helped shape Britain
and the world.
Dunksford Aerad Drrome is one of the
best preserved airfields in Britain.
With its historic buildings and hangers
full to the brim with beautifully
preserved aircraft, this is a place
where history isn't just alive and
kicking, it's flying.
Abandoned in the early 1960s, Duxford
was brought back to [music] life in 1977
when the Imperial War Museum, known as
the IWM, took control. It's now home to
an impressive collection of aircraft,
vehicles, weapons, and artifacts [music]
from different countries spanning over
100 years of history.
Duxford is, of course, of huge
historical significance in its own
right. Throughout the Second World War,
it was a key air base and was home not
just to some of Britain's most famous
fighter races, but also to the US 8th
Air Force. If like me, you have a
passion for planes, this is the place to
come.
Peter, very nice to see you.
>> Yes, good morning. Welcome to IWM
Duxford.
>> Peter, no trip to Duxford is ever
wasted. I guess for many people they
associate it with World War II, but its
history is much older than that.
>> Oh, yes. The um happily one of our
claims to fame is that we're actually a
superb preserved example of a first
world war RAF station. The site is
dominated by these enormous hangers.
When do these date from?
>> Yes, indeed. Construction of the three
big surviving historic hangers actually
began in October 1917. And one example
you can see straight away adjacent to
the hanger behind us is the first world
war flight hut which was extended during
the 1920s to incorporate the watch
office.
>> And what aircraft were those early
squadrons that were based here equipped
with?
>> The three squadrons that were mobilized
from here were equipped with air
dehavlin DH6 and DH9 biplanes. But the
main purpose of Duxford was as a
training depot station. And we have four
preserved examples of appropriate types
on site here. And if you'd care to join
me, I'd be delighted to show you a
couple.
>> I knew you'd have plenty.
>> This is one of the four airplane types
that the IWM has preserved which date
from the First World War. This is a
Royal Aircraft Factory B2C which were
used on the Western Front for
reconnaissance, artillery spotting and
light bombing. Now, unfortunately, it
was such a stable airplane that it was
actually it turned out to be unsuitable
>> for Western Front operations. Yeah. And
it couldn't maneuver in the face of of
enemy fighters. So, it had to be
withdrawn.
>> It's an incredibly rare survivor, isn't
it? But not to take away from the
aircraft, Peter, the building we're in
is absolutely beautiful. And of course,
it's dominated by these incredible
lattis beams. I suppose
>> the lattice work construction is very
impressive. It's very eye-catching. The
design term is Belfast Truss. You can
tell how durable it is simply because of
the age of the buildings and the fact
that the structure has survived some
very stormy weather. The buildings here,
these hangers are, I suppose, the jewel
in Duxford's crown in many respects. But
of course, it wasn't just about hangers.
A huge array of ancillary buildings
stretch out all around us. Can we go and
take a closer look at some of those?
>> Indeed. Yes. Let's go and have a look at
some of the stalls and workshops.
So along the road behind us, the green
buildings were First World Wars,
um, clothing stores, technical stores of
different types.
>> And what's this one with 1918 written on
it?
>> Yes. What looks like a chimney, it's
actually a fume extractor because this
was one of the most important of the
First World War workshops. It was the
fabric shop where they did the doping
cuz they had to have a way of getting
the fumes away from the chaps and the
girls working.
>> Well, the dope workshop was an infamous
place to be, wasn't it?
>> The hazard was recognized at one of the
counters, for example, was that the
staff were given an extra milk ration.
>> Yes. So, we're now approaching the front
entrance to the officer's mess.
>> It looks rather fullon there with all
the leaves, but it must have been a very
sumptuous building.
>> Yes, indeed. They they deliberately
tried to make the accommodations and
facilities as comfortable as possible
and quite impressive. Um, I can give you
an illustration. The uh this is actually
a very poignant photograph. It shows one
of the anti- rooms. So, it's the you can
see the windows.
>> The windows are a real giveaway, aren't
they?
>> Yeah. And this is actually some of the
station personnel, RAF and um army
liaison officers uh listening to the
declaration of war, the announcement
over the radio by the prime minister.
>> I mean the life of a fighter pilot was
one of great contrast, wasn't it, Peter?
From being up there engaging the enemy
to then landing and enjoying the
relative comforts of a mess like this.
>> Yeah, it it was a very important morale
factor.
>> And I'm kind of rather moved by the fact
that the greats kind of inhabited this
building, the likes of BA and others.
Yes indeed. And happily we can prove it
that if you take a very photograph
here's Sir Douglas as he later became
with two of his fellow pilots here in
1940 during the period of the Battle of
Britain. I think when you can place
yourself in a moment in time like this
with a photograph such as that one
outside a building that has the pedigree
and providence that this one does at
Duxford. It's quite moving, isn't it?
>> Oh, very much so.
Sir Douglas Ber was perhaps one of the
most legendary of Britain's World
[music] War II fighter aces. Credited
with 23 aerial victories, he joined the
RAF in 1928, but famously lost his legs
in a plane accident in 1931.
Although able to fly with artificial
legs, he was retired from the RAF
against his will. Only with the onset of
war in 1939 was he able to rejoin as a
pilot.
He convinced people at the air ministry
that he should be allowed back into the
RAF as a pilot and he came back to to
fly successfully uh not just as a
fighter pilot but as a very successful
fighter pilot and and as a squadron
leader and and then leading a whole
group of different [music] fighters from
this station during the battle of
Britain
>> in 1940 during the early stages of the
battle of Britain fighter command was
outnumbered in aerial combat. So to
conquer this the big wing [music] was
formed.
It consisted of three to five squadrons
made up of nearly 60 aircraft in diamond
[music] formations.
It was thought the more fighters
involved intercepting the enemy, the
more aircraft [music] they could
destroy.
Barter was a champion of this aggressive
idea.
On the 15th of September, when the
Dutford wing or big [music] wing as it
became known, was involved in combat
against the German formations twice on
that day. What it did do was certainly
persuade the Luftwaffer that, you know,
the the British Air Force wasn't
defeated by [music] any means. So, if
only from the morale point of view, you
know, Barter's big wing had a big impact
on the Germans. So, although Barter was,
you know, the most famous [music]
character connected with Duxford, there
were many other pilots here. Anyone time
between 60 to 80 pilots here. Anyone
from Barter through to George [music]
Unwin to Brian Lane, who was the
commanding officer of 19 Squadron. In a
sense, the successful aces were the few
of the few. Um, but those are the guys
did most of the shooting down of the
enemy aircraft, but they're supported by
other fighter pilots who up there maybe
protecting their back in combat. Duxford
was home to 15 squadrons with [music]
pilots drawn from all over the world
from Canadians to Czechoslovakians to
the Polish who had escaped the German
invasion.
>> So, we're standing inside the operations
room at RF Duxford. It's a
reconstruction of the room inside the
original building. So each airfield had
its squadrons [music] ready to go and if
there was an enemy raid coming in. The
operations room at Ducks would have been
told to get a squadron up in the air. So
the controller who sat on the dice
behind the ear, he could see where the
enemy formations were coming in on the
big map table. The squadrons would be
called to basically scramble, get in the
air, get off as fast as they could to
intercept the enemy formations. I
interviewed one of the guys who actually
worked [music] in these little radio
cabins here. He said, "One day B's
message just consists of six F words."
Some of his language was, you know,
notorious, shouting back to Wood or
like, "My eyes are standing up like dogs
bollocks, but I still can't see them.
Woody, where are they?" That sort of
thing. You know, obviously the BS were
under real stress. They were being shot
up in the sky, so things were pretty
tense.
>> Unlike the Hollywood films we see today
depicting aerial dog fights, in real
life, combat would only last a matter of
minutes. A Spitfire or Huracan could
fire off all of their rounds in just 15
seconds.
>> You wouldn't fly straight and level for
more than 30 seconds because you're
always afraid that someone's going to
get on your tail. Uh you're you're
focusing on trying to, you know, hit
your enemy. Could have been a big
target, a small target, but if you got
into combat with an enemy fighter, then
you're pulling really sharp turns, sharp
G's. You might even black out because
you're doing a fast turn. Maybe this
often happens when you, you know, uh,
I'm told when you're in combat that you
can end up in a completely empty sky.
There's no one else there at all and
it's all diseed. It's all gone and then
you're calling back to the operations
room for a fix to fly back to your home
base.
>> Dougford's RAF pilots played a critical
role during the war. Every day, on
average, 60 Spitfires and Huracans were
dispersed around the base.
The collections here at Duxford are
[music] unrivaled, and this is one
object that I think speaks volumes. This
is Douglas Bart's uniform, complete with
metal ribbons, including, of course, the
Distinguished Flying Cross. And it's
that level of detail here, that access
to the men behind the machines that
really do make this place come alive.
Today, Duxford's main role is in
preserving our aviation history.
Everything from photographs to buildings
to aircraft.
Now, not all items here at Duxford
arrive in pristine working condition.
Many have to be lovingly and
painstakingly restored, and that happens
over here.
Wow, this is amazing. If you're
interested in aircraft restoration,
James, this really is an Aladdin's cave,
isn't it? Yes, we've um this is the
aircraft restoration company. We look
after a fleet of around 40 historic
aircraft ranging from the P-51 Mustang,
which is uh the American's finest
fighter of the time.
>> But what a place. I mean, everything
that comes in and out of your doors
flies.
>> Yeah. Every single airplane we we
maintain, operates, and uh or restore
will end up flying from here.
>> And do you only deal with
propeller-driven aircraft? No, not only
propeller driven aircraft, we also look
after vintage jets. One of which is the
uh F86 Saber A model which is uh in the
hanger at the moment. It's the oldest
flying jet in the world currently. But
the range of skills you have to master
from jet propulsion to propellers to
varying types of airframe and materials.
It's an enormous challenge.
>> Yes, it is. It's huge. Um which is why
we've started our own apprenticeship
scheme as there are no longer the skills
around. uh in this country for us to
keep these aircraft flying.
>> But just as an example, how many hours
would it take a year to keep say that
beautiful P-51 Mustang in the air?
>> You'd be looking at around about 6 to 8
weeks of maintenance by a team of
engineers. Um round about four or five
weeks in the in the winter and then a
couple of weeks in the summer for oil
changes and and that sort of thing.
>> But I gather that you don't just
maintain and restore them, you also
build a good number from scratch.
>> Yes, we do.
>> Let's have a look at that.
As well as being a museum, Duxford is
home to around 20 to 30 historical
aircraft that are still flying.
From Supermarine Spitfires to the huge
B7 bomber, the Sally B.
Mo, nice to see you. I gather if anybody
knows how to build a Spitfire, it's you.
>> Apparently, so [laughter]
>> thank you very much, James. Cheers. Mo,
this is astonishing. Is this a
completely new wing? No, this wing is
for a Mark 11 Spitfire and we recovered
approximately 25% of the original parts.
>> So having that tiny percentage of an
original is enough to give the finished
aircraft the right sort of provenence.
>> That's right. Yeah. Yeah. 25% these days
is a lot to have. Yeah.
>> But just looking at this table in front
of me, these all look like brand new
>> components. This is a new side cowling.
Quite often the side cings don't exist
with a project. They're things that get
taken off and lost. So most of the time
they're made as a completely new item.
>> Can you give me an example of one of
those skills that you've had to sort of
relearn as it were?
>> Yeah. One of the main ones is wheeling.
And I can show you a good example of
that over here.
>> Now this this leading edge skin here is
um because it's a double curve shape.
You can't just roll it in one direction.
You need to wheel it to shrink and
stretch the material.
>> You say wheel it actually put a wheel
over it. It's nipped between two wheels
and that that stretches the materials in
different directions
>> because that is a really
>> iconic bit of the Spitfire. That's
right.
>> This wonderful elliptical shape. I mean,
there isn't really a straight line on
it.
>> No. No. And that that poses the problem
for shaping the material.
>> The satisfaction you and your guys must
get from seeing an aircraft 18 months
later roll out of the hanger onto the
runway and get airborne.
>> Yeah, it's great. You've seen the
project from from birth to end and then
you know it's going to go flying around
the country for people to enjoy.
>> During the 1930s and 40s over 20,000
Spitfires were built.
Today through restoration and
preservation there are around 28 still
flying in the UK and over 50 worldwide.
Well, Duxford was the first fighter
airfield to take delivery of this, the
now legendary Spitfire. And it's also a
first for me because I've got my chance
at long last to get airborne in one with
lovely Cliff. Good to see you, mate.
>> And you.
>> I cannot tell you how excited I am to
finally get my chance to experience what
this beautiful aircraft is all about in
its natural environment up there.
>> Well, you've picked the right day,
>> haven't we? Just blue sky.
>> Blue sky. Everything's going for us.
>> No wind. And this Yeah. Now, tell us a
little more about this particular
aircraft. clip.
>> It's quite a famous Spitfire. All
Spitfires are famous, but this one was
built in 1944 and actually flew at D-Day
and it's got four victories to its
credit. So, you're flying in quite an
important airplane. In those days, of
course, it was a single seater and uh
it's converted after the war into a
two-seater, which is good for you
because I'm not sure you could
[laughter] go solo on your first trip.
>> It's my chance to finally do it. But how
astonishing that this aircraft saw
D-Day. saw that great Armada assembling
off the Normandy beaches.
>> Absolutely. Absolutely did. And indeed,
it's painted in the colors that it was
at that time uh in 1944. So, if I were
to take to the skies in a Spitfire, this
arguably is the one to do it.
>> Absolutely.
>> Well, Cliff, I've got you to fly me.
We've got this incredible aircraft.
We've got the most stunning blue sky
above us. Should we get on and get up?
>> Let's go and do it. I am too excited.
>> Right. There you go.
>> And lower myself down.
>> Yep.
>> All right.
>> Okay. Elbow through there.
And we'll do the same with the other
side.
Just pull those part and slide it over
the head.
>> Good stuff.
>> Good stuff. Well done. Well done.
>> See you at the other end.
>> Yeah. Right.
>> Well, I am strapped in. My parachute is
on under my backside and we are about to
get airborne. This really is a dream
come true. A flight in a genuine World
War II Spitfire. Let's go.
What a wonderful noise.
>> Yes. Isn't it a lovely noise? It's uh 27
L Rolls-Royce Merlin 60 series 1600
horsepower.
Unbelievable.
Oh god, I'm actually
skate. I was hugely inspired by the B.
You can see it from the air from a
spitfire. Look at that.
And of course, these aircraft would have
been scrambled in seconds and then
directed to the enemy by the incredible
work of the ground controllers relying
so heavily on radar.
But imagine it, Cliff, taking off on a
day like this when you can see almost
nothing else in the sky but knowing the
enemy, the bandits are out there
somewhere. Absolutely.
Many pilots talk of the aircraft being
an extension of themselves. I can
absolutely see what they meant.
I feel like I have shrouded wings as
Cliff brings his in over the airfield at
over 200 knots. There we go. And up into
a climb,
a bank to the left. And then the
airfield above me. Oh, beautiful.
Beautiful.
There we are.
Oh, the grace of this aircraft has to be
felt to be believed.
There we go.
And we're done.
Yes. Yes. Yes.
>> Well, I've been coming to this airfield
ever since I was a boy. I've watched the
museum develop and grow. I never really
thought I would ever get the chance to
see it from the air or to see it from a
Spitfire, but today really has been my
lucky day. Cliff, thank you. Thank you
very much indeed.
Before operational bases like Duxford
received their Spitfires, the pilots
would need tuition. And this happened at
[music] training bases. But with most of
the men at war, the role of maintaining
the aircraft was left to the women's
auxiliary air force. They weren't
allowed to go into combat, but they did
fulfill many ground crew roles from
radar to engineering.
The men had all been sent off to
operational stations and the ones that
weren't operational were getting short
of mechanics. That's when they made the
girls mechanics.
When a pilot had done so many hours
flying, operational flying, he was had
to come and have a sort of break and a
retrain.
And that's when we looked after the
aircraft. And every time they flew, we
did a quick inspection. Well, we changed
the wheels and we did everything more or
less the outside of the aircraft.
Screwed things on and screwed things off
and one thing and another. But when the
pilot had to take it for a test flight
and he had the engines going, two of us
had to sit on the tail of the Spitfire
because with the thrust of the props
going round, it would have tipped up. So
we used to sit on the tail until we
turned into the runway. Then you jumped
off. Well, one girl didn't jump off.
She was lying across the tail and got
airborne.
And when the pilot wanted to bank or was
just turned, he couldn't cuz his what
they call the ailerons wouldn't work. So
he had to get a emergency landing. And
when he he got landed and this girl
jumped off, poor man was
he was terrified. He thought he'd killed
her. By July 1943, the Women's Auxiliary
Air Force had swelled to around 182,000,
serving in over 110 different trades.
The Supermarine Spitfire wasn't the only
star to be based at Duxford.
In 1943, the Aer Drrome was assigned to
the United States Army Air Force, the
USAAF,
and it became known as station 357.
Within a few weeks of the Americans
moving in, Duxford became a showcase for
the Eighth Air Force with plenty of
famous visitors.
>> Well, what better place to dive into the
archive, Carl, than here at Duxford
Cinema. This is incredible footage. When
did the Americans arrive here?
>> The Americans arrived here in April
1943. You can see on the footage there
that this is shortly after they arrived
when the the king and queen visited. And
they very quickly sort of made Duxford
their home. You know, they very quickly
changed the atmosphere, I suppose,
changed the atmosphere of the whole
region because you can't just plunk
2,000 guys down in the middle of the
Cambridge countryside for them to not
have an effect.
>> For many people, Duxford is synonymous
with the Battle of Britain and the
American involvement here is perhaps a
little bit unappreciated.
>> That's right. And if you think about it
in terms of the overall conduct of the
war, Britain is on the defensive in
1940,
it's very much a defensive effort and
Duxford is part of that defensive
effort. But then when the Americans
arrive, that that very much signals that
the war is going on the offensive. And
of course, that's what they're there to
do. They're there to take part in that
strategic bombing offensive. But I
suppose they bring with them a great
sense of optimism. Britain's been at war
for several years. It's feeling the
strain. And yet here come these new
young, fit, freshfaced boys who are keen
to re-energize the fight.
>> There's a lot in that. I think
particularly Britain had been at war for
quite a long time. It was a bit warw
weary. It was a bit shabby. And you know
these guys were coming over with an
enormous amount of economic might. They
could build 12,000 B7s, build the
fighters.
>> But they also clearly bring a real sense
of glamour and exoticism to Cambridge.
They brought a real sense of glamour of
other worldliness. You know, it was
called a friendly invasion. And there
are two parts to that. Yes, it was
friendly, but it I guess for a lot of
people it did feel like an invasion
because all of these people from a
completely different culture were
suddenly descending and having to mix
and having to exchange their cultures in
a quite a sort of intensive way,
>> but also a tide of celebrities to go
with it.
>> Absolutely. So, um, not only did many of
them sound like film stars, some of them
were actually film stars. people like
Clark Gable, Jimmy Stewart, um, all
doing their bit, you know, and then of
course you had celebrities who were
deliberately flown over to entertain the
troops. So people like Bob Hope, people
like Bing Crosby.
>> But I'm reminded of that great phrase
that emerged from the American invasion,
if you will, of them being overpaid,
over sexed, and over here.
>> I think the one of the most interesting
responses I I saw to that was an
American who said that the Brits were
underpaid, under sexed, and under
Eisenhower. [laughter]
Yes, of course.
>> To pay tribute to the 30,000 American
airmen who gave their lives flying from
UK bases, the American Air Museum was
opened at Duxford. It's home to an
impressive array of American aircraft
from World War II to modern day.
This beautiful, purpose-built American
hanger here at Duxford is packed with
examples of the aircraft the Americans
produced. That's a B7. Above me, the
tail fin of a Marauder. up there, a C-47
Dakota. The whole thing is dominated by
this enormous B-52, but it also contains
examples of two of the aircraft that the
USAF brought here in April 1943. The
P-47 Thunderbolt and over there, the
P-51 Mustang. And of course, with the
planes came the pilots. One of these
pilots was Huey Lamb of the 82nd Fighter
Squadron. He amassed over 200 hours of
combat flying, destroying five enemy
aircraft in 61 missions.
Originally from Texas, he found the
British climate difficult to get used
to. We'd been on the Queen Mary for a
week or two, and
I hadn't had a a freshwater shower, so I
took a shower and it was ice cold. And
then after that, I never got warm while
I was over. It was chilly.
>> When Lamb's 78th Fighter Group initially
moved to Duxford, they brought with them
the largest and heaviest fighter in
history to be powered by a single
engine, the P47 Thunderbolt.
When fully loaded with its eight machine
guns and bombs, the P47 weighed a
staggering 8 tons.
When we got over here, we had a
different opinion of the P47. And the
reason was that they used 100 octane gas
here and when we were training, they use
80 octane. So, it made that much
difference. It's just it's just amazing
how much difference. And we really
respected the ability of the P47. And we
also had a very good high alitude
airplane with a a big uh supercharger
and a excellent lowaltitude airplane for
strafing and ground work.
>> In 1944, [music] Lamb made history as
only the third 78th Fighter Group pilot
to down the world's first operational
jet powered fighter, a German Mesid 262.
The kill took place during one of many
low-level strafing missions. And
although they were effective in
destroying enemy targets, they also made
the attacking aircraft vulnerable from
the ground.
>> You know, it's hard to imagine, but most
of the people that were in our outfit
wanted the dangerous missions. January,
February of 45,
we got a new CO, Colonel Gray, and he
went up to headquarters, and he said,
"I'm going to get you guys some good
missions." That meant get some action.
And so, we got some good missions after
that.
>> In December 1944, the 82nd Fighter
Squadron were fitted out with new
fighters, the P-51 Mustang.
Lamb flew two Mustangs, both named Eta
Jane after his little sister.
The first one, however, didn't survive
the war. On his very first mission out,
the aircraft suffered an engine fire,
forcing him to ditch it into the
freezing North Sea.
I thought I was going to make it to the
shore at Arford Nest. About 3 miles off
there, you'll find Edene the First. It's
about 100 ft down in the ocean there. My
right wing stalled and caught a wave and
it cartw wheeled and that saved me
because if it if I'd have landed
straight, there's a scoop underneath the
P21 that would have brought it straight
down. And I was also fortunate that I
had people that saw it go in and then my
wingman, his radio was out and I was
bringing him back when this happened and
and he flew and saw a walrus
taxing out and he landed, set the brakes
and told him that he had a man down and
he'd lead them to me. It was, you know,
it didn't fly very fast and and he would
circle and then head out, then circle
and head out and then they landed and
picked me up. I didn't know it, but they
had six attempts to start their engine
and it finally got it started. So, I've
been lucky all along. You know,
everybody needs luck.
>> Today, Huey Lamb has returned to Duxford
and the American Air Museum. He's here
for the unveiling of a brand new museum
exhibit. The reason I'm I'm here for
this visit is they have restored a P-51
and put the markings identical to Edene
the second that the plane I flew in
combat here. Everything just as it was
and that's the reason I'm back here to
see it.
Well, naturally it makes me want to fly
fly it period.
By 1944, the United States Army Air
Force had deployed some 450,000
Americans to Britain. And with only 7%
of those being pilots, the majority
[music] were ground crew.
The American invasion that had swept
across Britain, filling the country with
thousands of young men, brought with it
the possibility for tension. [music] And
in a bit to try and iron it out, the
American authorities issued their troops
with this. Instructions for American
servicemen in Britain, 1942. Now, the
book is pretty simple, but its message
was vitally important, and it begins
with this. You're going to Great Britain
as part of an Allied offensive to meet
Hitler and beat him on his own ground.
But for the time being, you will be
Britain's guest. And it reminds the
American that Britain may look a little
shopworn and grimy to you. The British
people are anxious to have you know that
you're not seeing their country at its
best. There's been a war on since 1939.
But it's also quite amusing. I love this
one. The British don't know how to make
a good cup of coffee. You don't know how
to make a good cup of tea. It's an even
swap. And so it goes on. It is always
impolite to criticize your hosts. It is
militarily stupid to criticize your
allies. And that was what it was all
about. If the Allied cause could not be
[music] united at every level, it would
never stand any chance of success.
During the period of World War II, about
2 million Americans would pass through
Britain. Many would be stationed in East
Anglia, where they became a common site,
flooding the nearby towns during their
time off.
During the war, Cambridge was very much
a social hub for the American GIS and
airmen stationed around air bases in
East Anglia. Behind me here we have the
Bull Hotel as it was which was converted
by the American Red Cross. The Red Cross
clubs were really providing a home away
from home for the Americans. They could
read magazines and newspapers that had
been shipped in from the United States.
They listened to American music on the
jukebox and there was plenty of
Coca-Cola, coffee and donuts on hand to
really make them feel at home. But the
one thing the Red Cross clubs didn't
have is alcohol. They weren't licensed.
So the GIs would have to go to the local
pubs if they wanted to get a drink. And
in Cambridge, that meant a trip to the
Eagle.
>> Already popular with RAF air crews, the
American servicemen continued the
tradition of inscribing the numbers of
their flight squadrons on the ceiling of
the Eagle. Using lighters, candles, and
lipstick, the Americans left their
[music] mark. But it was their
personalities that left a stronger
impression.
When the Americans first arrived, there
was a certain degree of suspicion about
them coming from the British people. Um,
often they felt that they didn't look
like an army in the way that they
expected them to. They didn't march uh
quite as rigidly as the British men.
Partly this was because the Brits only
saw the Americans when they were off
duty, you know, when they were out
having a good time. And often there was
this kind of idea that are these really
the people who are going to save us?
They don't seem up to the job. The
British women for the most part came to
really appreciate the Americans. They
had a real allure. Partly this was
because for British girls mostly they'd
never seen an American in their life
apart from at the cinema. So when the
GIS came over they had this uh aura of
Hollywood glamour attached to them.
The first time I ever saw the Americans
were the time when we uh, my friend and
I came out of the dance and we heard the
wolf whistle and and wondered who are
these people in [music] these uniforms.
We had never seen them before. They were
very handsome and nice manners and they
smelled nice too.
They had lovely cologne on which our
poor guys. I feel sorry for them because
I had a brother in the the army. They
weren't um able to get all this stuff.
[music]
>> The Americans were advised not to brag
too much to the local people or not to
swank as they called [music] it at the
time. But in fact, a lot of them did.
One woman actually married an American
guy who had told her that he was in oil.
But when she got over to the United
States, it turned out that he [music]
was a gas pump attendant. The American
salaries were more than five times that
paid to British troops, making their
generosity particularly attractive to
women. Around 70,000 British women
became GI brides and around 9,000 babies
were born out of wedlock as a result of
British American liaison.
>> Um, the first American that I knew and I
I was so fond of him. And can I can I
read this for you?
If I can if I can get through it. It
always makes me a little bit tearary,
but never mind. He was 22 and I was 17.
I thought he was lovely and he seemed
very keen. But he was a bomber pilot.
Didn't stand a chance. When singled out
by fighters shot down over France. That
evening, as usual, I waited. His friend
came instead. I sobbed as he told me my
lovely friend was dead. Since then I've
loved a dozen times, but first love so
sincere. Remember him? Of course I do,
especially this time of the year.
So that was the first time that anything
like that really hit me. But it
happened. You you'd have a date and your
date wouldn't turn up and somebody else
would say, "Oh, him. Oh, he didn't come
back from [music]
such and such." and you'd think I can't
I can't be doing with this. I just
can't.
>> Betty met a number of Americans and at a
dance one particular GI took a liking to
her.
>> He would call me and we'd meet in London
[music] and dance again as you do at the
pal or wherever it was and [music] have
a lovely time. And then one day after
the war had been over, he phoned me up
and he said,
"Would you would you marry me?" It was a
bit of a shock. I hadn't thought about
getting married. I must admit it wasn't
something in my diary for the next day
or week or month.
Besides, I was still sort of still
hankering after my soldier that had gone
overseas.
Anyway, not to worry.
When the GIS left, they left a real void
for many of the British people who'd
grown used to them being around. They'd
grown used to these cheery
personalities, to their charm and their
wit and their good manners. Um, and they
really missed them. Just a month after
the end of the war in October 1945, the
Americans left Duxford and the base was
returned to the RAF.
But by 1961, Duxford was deemed too far
south and too far inland to be of any
strategic value and it was abandoned.
In 1977, the Imperial War Museum gave
the site a new lease of life. The museum
needed a bigger site outside of London
to exhibit their larger displays and
house their conservation workshops.
These workshops are one of my favorite
parts of the museum here at Duxford
because their contents change year upon
year, month upon month. You never quite
know what you're going to find. Take
this for example. This field gun is the
field gun that fired the first British
round during the First World War.
They've just cleaned it up. This is the
front end of a Handy Page Halifax and
next to it a post-war Spanish-built
Hankle. This one starred in the movie
The Battle of Britain. But take a look
over here. This is extraordinary. This
is the fuselage of the Meshmith that
Rudolph Hess was flying when he landed
in Scotland and was captured. But of
course, it's not just the old stuff they
deal with here. You'd be surprised at
some of the new material that's coming
through every day.
This is perhaps my favorite part of the
museum. You get to see all the jewels in
the collection passing through here at
some point, don't you?
>> As well as preserving the aircraft and
the vehicles that we work on, we're
trying to preserve the skills so that we
can maintain these objects as they
should be maintained.
>> Now, I can't help but notice Huey Lamb's
Mustang sitting over there in half.
What's going on over there?
>> Right. What's happening with this
aircraft? We're going to be suspending
it when we refurbish the American Air
Museum next year. So on this aircraft,
because there is a natural joint there,
we've separated it. We're going to put
in a fish plate reattached to the
empanage. So we just have a small loop
protruding above the fuselage and then
we can suspend it like that. And it's
less intrusive than a lot of systems
you'll see.
>> So what's the biggest project that's
come through your hands here?
>> The biggest project I personally dealt
with is the B-52. We had to paint strip
that aircraft completely, repair skin
panels that had been corroded, left
outside, and then repaint it.
>> That must be the biggest aircraft here.
Surely
>> it is the biggest aircraft we have in
our collection. It's 185 ft wingspan. I
believe it's about 165 ft long, about 50
foot high. So yes, it was a big big
project.
>> You have had the chance in your time
here to have in your care some of the
real gems in the museum's collection.
What's your favorite item?
>> My favorite item, I suppose really, if I
had to push it, would be the engine we
have over there from the Baron von
Richtoven's tripling. As a child and a
young boy at school, I was fascinated by
fight races in the First World War. So
to actually touch that, handle it, and
make decisions on its future is really
quite something.
>> Let me just get this absolutely
straight. You're telling me that over
there is the Red Baron's engine from his
Fauler triplane? Yeah. From his [__]
DR1 that he was shot down here.
[laughter] Yes.
>> You see, that's why I love this place,
Chris. You never know what you're going
to find. This is a place to me where
history is so alive and so tangible. You
can reach out and touch it. And you get
to do that on a daily basis.
>> Yes, it's different and there's so much
variety. Any given day, I might be
dealing with a First World War fighter.
I might be dealing with an SR71. I might
be dealing with Baron von Retoven's
engine. Could be anything. I don't know
very often what's going to come across
my desk on any given day.
>> How exciting is that? Well, thank you
very much indeed. I can see that there's
plenty of work going on here. Plenty
more still to do before this aircraft is
hung from the ceiling. But um next time
we build an FX model, I'll think of you.
>> By preserving the vintage aircraft and
the stories of the Aer Drrome, Duxford's
vital role during World War II will
never be forgotten.
>> As a kid, Duxford was the first airfield
I ever visited. And nearly 40 years
later, I'm still exploring it. The
collections here are second to none.
This is a place where the story not just
of British aviation, but of world
aviation, is so accessible and so
tangible, you can virtually taste it.
The Duxford story itself [music] has
inspired countless generations, both
past and present. And I have absolutely
no [music] doubt that it'll continue to
do so long into the future.
>> [music]